欢迎来到 Startup School 2026，我们现在开始吧
Welcome to Startup School 2026. Now let's get started.
请和我一起欢迎 NVIDIA 创始人兼 CEO Jensen Huang（黄仁勋）登台
Please join me in welcoming to the stage the founder and CEO of NVIDIA, Jensen Huang.
嘿，Garry
Hey, Garry.
大家请坐
Please, everybody.
天哪
Oh, my God.
这一刻对我来说太不真实了。谢谢你，谢谢你能来
This is a surreal moment for me. Thank you. Thank you for being here.
我很高兴能来，很高兴来到这里
Jensen I'm delighted to do it. It's great to be here.
据说，只要你能来到这里，你就一定会成功
Apparently, if you're here, you are gonna make it.
所以我很开心能在这里
So I'm happy I'm here.
对于那些只知道 NVIDIA 是如今 AI 中心的学生来说
Jensen well, for the students who only know NVIDIA as a company at the center of AI,
NVIDIA 早期故事里，最需要他们理解的是哪一部分
what part of the early NVIDIA story do they most need to understand?
大多数人不敢相信的一点是
The thing that most people don't, don't believe is that that, um, uh,
我们创办公司时选择的技术路线是完全错误的
the choice of our technology that we started the company with was absolutely wrong.
我们一开始的想法是要重新发明 3D 图形技术
And so we had started with the idea that we would reinvent 3D graphics.
公司的理念和视角是
Well, the, the company's philosophy and perspective, uh,
通用计算机
was that the general purpose computers,
也就是 CPU，确实很有用，但如果我们能用加速器来增强它
the CPUs were really useful but if we could augment it with uh, accelerators,
就能解决原本难以解决的问题
we could solve problems that otherwise too hard to solve.
我们最早选择的问题之一就是 3D 图形
And one of the first problems we chose was 3D graphics.
那是在 1993 年，当时 PC 只是传闻中即将出现的东西
And we, and during that time, 1993, the PC was just rumored to be coming.
我们的大想法是把每一台个人电脑都变成
And, and our big idea was that we would turn every single personal computer into a
一台游戏主机，因为我们是在游戏主机的时代长大的
game console, because we grew up in the era of game consoles.
所以我们想，如果我们能够
And so we thought, you know what, if we could, could, um,
设计一个能装进个人电脑的系统
design a system that would fit into the personal computer
把它变成一台游戏主机就好了
and it would turn it into a game console.
于是我们想重新发明一种算法
And so we thought we would reinvent the algorithm
把原本需要大型超级计算机才能跑的东西塞进 PC 里
that would require these large supercomputers and we would fit it into the PC.
我们提出了一些新的算法
And we came up with some new algorithms.
我们对此很兴奋，也很相信它
And we were excited about it. We believed in it.
我们经过深思熟虑地推理
It was, we reasoned about it in a thoughtful way and,
然后就去创办公司，把它做出来
and we went to start the company to go build it.
结果证明这个算法恰恰是错的
Well, turns out the algorithm was exactly wrong and the technology
我们创办公司所依据的技术也恰恰是错的
that founded the company turns out to be exactly wrong.
到了 1995 年我们才意识到这一点，而那几乎已经太晚了
And so in 1995, we realized that and it was almost too late
因为那时候已经有大约 35
because by then there were some 35,
40 家其他公司在为 PC 开发 3D 图形技术了
40 other companies that were building 3D graphics for PCs.
于是我们意识到，这条路走不通
And, and so we realized that it didn't work.
我回到公司，大家都在公司里，我说
And I went back to the company and we were at the company. I said,
我们该怎么办
what are we going to do?
这行不通，我们都在讨论这件事
It doesn't work. And we're all talking about it.
我说，听着
And I said, look, we, we, uh, we,
如果我们不去正视这条路行不通这个事实，公司就完了
we won't have a company if we don't confront the fact that this doesn't work
我们得开始朝着正确的算法路线努力
and start working towards the right algorithm.
然后有人告诉我
And, and then somebody told me,
结果我们当中没有一个人知道正确的做法是什么
it turns out none of us knew how to do it the right way
我们不仅选错了技术
and not only did we choose the wrong technology,
而且根本不知道该怎么正确地去做
we didn't know how to do it the right way.
所以那对我来说是重大的一天
And so, so that, that was a big day for me.
我口袋里当时只有几十美元，也就几百美元吧
I had a couple, couple of $60, you know, a couple hundred dollars in my pocket.
于是我跑去 Fry's，买了三本教材
And so I went down to Fry's and I bought three textbooks and.
那些教材讲的是 OpenGL，以及如何设计 OpenGL 流水线
And the textbooks was about OpenGL and how to design OpenGL pipelines.
我把它们带回公司，交给工程师们，然后就有了今天
I brought it back to the company and gave it to the engineers and here we are.
我们重塑了计算机图形，成为现代计算机图形领域的世界领导者
We reinvented computer graphics. We're the world leader in modern computer graphics.
过去 25 年里大多数重大突破都是我们发明的
We invented most of the major breakthroughs in the last 25 years.
所有人都会以为 NVIDIA
Everybody would have thought that NVIDIA is, you know,
一开始就是 3D 图形领域的世界领导者，可我们是从教材里学来的
started out as world leaders in 3D graphics and we Learned it from a textbook.
所以我们其实是先创办了公司
And so we actually started the company,
融了钱，然后去买教材——仔细想想真是这样
raised money and bought textbooks when you think about it.
所以这里最大的教训是
And so the, the, the big lesson is
对我来说，技术一直在不断变化
that for me is technology is changing all the time.
只要你能够面对现实
And so long as you're able to confront the reality,
只要你能够学习，技术本身其实并不重要
so long as you are able to learn the technology itself actually doesn't matter.
从那以后，NVIDIA 就一直在
And so since then, NVIDIA has been, you know,
不断发明各种各样的技术
inventing all kinds of technology since,
各种我们以前从没真正做过的技术
all kinds of technology we've never really done before.
我们用同样的态度对待一切，就是说
And we approach everything with the same attitude, you know, this is,
如果这件事值得做，我们就去学
if it's important to do, we're going to go learn it.
这能有多难
And how hard can it be?
而它总是比我们预期的难得多得多
And it always turns out to be much, much harder than, than we expect.
但你带着这样的态度去做：这能有多难
But you go into it with the attitude, how hard can it be?
我是说，我们在后台聊到
I mean, backstage we were talking about how, I mean,
我们跟一些顶尖的 YC 公司聊过，你说
we were talking with some of the top YC companies and you were saying
每一家都在某个你不擅长的领域有专长
that each one has expertise in like a domain that you haven't.
你和 NVIDIA 也在某个领域有专长，它们都是，我忘了你怎么说的
You and NVIDIA have an expertise in and they're all just, I forget what you said,
大概是某种算法领域
it was like an algorithmic domain of a sort.
所以听起来 3D 图形只是算法领域中的第一个
And so it sounds like 3d graphics was merely the first of an algorithmic domain.
没错。它来自一本教材，但话说回来
That's right. And it came from a textbook, but then, you know,
任何人都能读到那本教材
anyone could have read that textbook.
你们做出了粒子物理、流体力学。是的，但你们创造出了
You created particle physics, fluid dynamics. Yeah, but you created the,
人们想要的东西，就像那种
the thing that people want, like the.
人们愿意花大价钱买的最终产品
The end product that people want to pay a lot of money for.
这家公司真正押对的大想法是
The big idea of the company that was spot on is
可以增强 CPU，去解决那些
that it is possible to augment the CPU to solve problems
原本太难解决的问题
that otherwise are too difficult to solve.
分子动力学是其中之一，图像处理是其中之一
And, and uh, molecular dynamics is one of them, image processing is one of them,
逆物理是另一个
inverse physics is another one.
还有各种各样不同的算法，当然
And so all kinds of different algorithms, of course,
深度学习是其中最重要的之一
deep learning is one of the major ones.
为了打造出今天这样的公司
And, and in order to create the company that we have today,
我们很早就意识到，关键不是造一颗很棒的芯片
we realized early on that it's not about building a great chip,
而是加速一个算法领域
it's about accelerating an algorithm domain.
我一直坚信的一件事是
And so one of the things that I've always believed,
成就伟大公司的，是对世界的一种独特视角
believed in is what makes great companies is a unique perspective about the world
一种你深信不疑的视角
that you deeply believe in.
关键不完全在于技术
It's not so much the technology,
也不完全在于市场，尽管这些都很重要
it's not so much the market even those things all matter.
如果你在正确的时间、为正确的市场，拥有正确的技术
And if you have the right technology for the right market at the right time,
你的日子会好过很多
your life is going to be a lot easier.
对某件重要事物未来的一种高层次愿景
A high level vision about the future of some important thing,
一种独特而你深信不疑的视角
a perspective about it that's somehow unique that you deeply believe in
而且最好，追求这个愿景是很难做到的
and ideally pursuing that vision is hard to do.
这些是很好的组合。对我们来说
Those are kind of good, good combinations. In our case,
我们意识到加速计算将会非常重要
we realized that accelerated computing was going to be important.
而加速计算最终确实非常重要
And accelerated computing turns out to be very important.
我们的洞察是，一切都与算法有关，而不是芯片
And our realization is everything to do with algorithm, not the chip.
结果证明完全正确
It turns out to be exactly right.
你讲了很多关于创始人所经历的艰辛
So you've said a lot about, I guess, the hardships of a founder.
有没有几个特别让你印象深刻的故事
Are there a few stories that really jump out at you?
我是说，在座的各位都很想创业，但是
I mean, the people in this room would love to start a company, but, you know,
他们真的准备好去啃硬骨头
are they really prepared for eating glass and, you know,
甚至可能要关掉公司、事情出岔子了吗
possibly having to shut down the company, like things going wrong.
有哪些真正让你难忘的关键时刻
Like, what are some of the pivotal moments that really jump out at you?
我记得你刚去过日本，对吧？是的，你当时好像是在致敬
I think you were just in Japan, right? And, uh, yeah, you were sort of, um, honoring,
Sega（世嘉），是吗
uh, Sega, was it?
我觉得那是个很有力量的故事
So I feel like that was a really powerful story.
让我们意识到自己选错算法路线的那个项目
The project that led us to realize the algorithm we chose was wrong was a
是和 Sega 的一次合作。Sega 当时委托我们打造
partnership with Sega. Sega, uh, had contracted us to build the.
Saturn 之后的那台游戏主机，也就是后来的 Dreamcast
Game console after Saturn that turned out to have been Dreamcast.
我不知道有没有人知道 Dreamcast 是什么
I don't know if does anybody know what Dreamcast is?
好吧，所以我们并没有造出 Dreamcast
Okay, so we did not build Dreamcast.
我们最初本该为 Dreamcast 做开发
We were originally supposed to build Dreamcast,
但因为我们的算法和技术从根本上就有缺陷
but because our algorithm and our technology was fundamentally flawed,
我去了日本，告诉 Isao Okawa
I went to Japan and I told Isao Okawa,
也就是当时的 CEO
the CEO at the time that that the contract
他们给我们的那份合同大概值 1200 万美元。我们没法……
that they gave us was like $12 million contract. We will not be able to, to.
没法完成，因为技术根本行不通
Fulfill because the technology doesn't work.
我把原因告诉了他，然后建议他们
And I told him the reasons why and then I advised that
另找别人来做这件事
that they choose somebody else to do it.
但接着我又对他说，很遗憾，我还是需要这笔钱
But then I asked him, I told him that I unfortunately still need the money.
他就问我，你可以想象那段对话
And he asked me, you could just imagine the conversation.
你的意思是，我委托你做的事你做不了
So what you're telling me is what I contract you to do, you can't do,
但你还想要合同里的全部钱
but you would like all the money on the contract.
我说，没错，就是这样
And I said, you got it. That's exactly right.
当然，我很礼貌，也很谦逊
But obviously, I was polite, I was humble.
他意识到我是诚实的，而且这一切都合情合理
And he realized that, that I was honest and, and, and, and everything made sense.
如果他不给我们这笔钱，我们就得关门了
I, and if he didn't give us the money, we'd be out of business.
我觉得这种事在这个圈子里也会发生。你投的不是公司
And I think that this happens in this room. You don't invest in companies.
你投的是人
You invest in people.
Okawa 先生看到的是
And what Okawa-san recognized was here's, you know,
一个他从一开始就信任的人和公司，那份合同
somebody and a company that he trusted in the first place, the contract,
一个他相信、也希望能看到它撑下去的团队
and that he believed in and that he would love to see, you know, make it,
撑到第二天
make it to the next day.
所以那 500 万美元让我们活了下来
And so that $5 million kept us alive and, you know,
给了我足够的时间去弄清楚该做什么
gave me enough time to discover what to do.
我听说，他们后来把它以 1500 万美元卖掉了
And then I guess if they held, they sold it for 15 million, I heard.
是的，我们一上市他们就卖了。NVIDIA 上市时
But yeah, they sold it the moment we went public. Uh, when NVIDIA went public,
我们的估值是 3 亿美元
our valuation was $300 million.
1999 年的 3 亿美元，那可是真金白银
$300 million in 1999. That was real money.
我想现在应该超过 1 万亿美元了。远不止如此
I think it's, uh, north of $1 trillion now or so. It's more than true.
是啊，太夸张了
Yeah, yeah. That's wild.
你算是核心人物，我们喜欢说
So you're sort of the core, you know, I, we like to say that you're, uh,
你是掌控香料的那个人
you're the man who controls the spice.
在那之前
Um, you know, before that, you know,
我觉得没人真能预料到
I don't think anyone could have really predicted per se, um, how important, uh,
GPU 和你打造的技术对这场 AI 革命会有多重要
GPUs and, you know, the technology you built would be for this AI revolution?
你到底看到了什么，我是说
Um, you know, what did you see to, I mean,
是加速器加上恰好在对的地方
was it the accelerator and being in the right place,
对的时间吗，还是说其实有很多因素累积起来
right time or surely there were a lot of things that led up to that,
才让你占据了这个位置
that allowed you to sort of capture this position?
是的
Yeah.
我和所有人一样看到了 AlexNet
I, I saw AlexNet just like everybody else saw AlexNet and, and, um,
但别忘了我们看世界的视角
but remember our lens of the world,
我看世界的方式一直是在寻找算法
my view of the world was always looking for algorithms.
那个算法可能是 NAMD，可能是 VASP
And that algorithm, the algorithm could be NAMD, the algorithm could be VASP,
可能是 OpenGL，可能是 SQL，某种领域专用语言，某种算法
the algorithm could be OpenGL, it could be SQL, some domain specific language, some algorithm.
所以我看世界的视角一直是在寻找某个
And so my lens of the world was always looking for some problem
我们或许能帮忙解决的问题
that we might be able to help solve.
当 AlexNet 出现时，那个算法就是深度学习
When AlexNet came along, the algorithm was deep learning.
于是问题就是，这个算法是什么，为什么它重要
And so the question is, what is this algorithm and why does it matter?
它为什么这么有效？它还能做什么
Why was it so effective? And what else can it do?
如果你把算法扩展，扩展到更大规模
And, and if you were to scale algorithms and scale it beyond that,
它能解决哪些今天原本无法解决的问题
what could it solve that otherwise you can't solve today?
对我们来说，真正的突破是意识到 AlexNet 并不只是 AlexNet
And the, the breakthrough for us was realizing that AlexNet was not AlexNet
AlexNet 是一种基于深度学习的方法
that AlexNet was an approach with deep learning
它能让你学会任何函数
that allows you to learn any function.
所以 15 年前，我就在告诉大家，你猜怎么着
And so 15 years ago, I was telling everybody that, hey, guess what?
我们刚刚学会了通用函数逼近器
We just Learned the universal function approximator.
我们刚刚发现了通用函数逼近器
We just discovered the universal function approximator.
我们可以给它
We can give it, we could, you know, give it the,
几乎任何函数的答案，它就能学会那个函数是什么
the answer for almost any function and it could learn what the function is.
对很多函数来说，你不需要做到精确。事实上
And for a lot of functions, you don't have to be precise. And in fact,
想精确也不可能
it's impossible to be precise.
所以大多数有意思的问题，都是这样不精确的
And so most of the interesting problems are imprecise in this way.
所以当我们意识到自己有了一个通用函数逼近器的那天
And so the day that we realize we have a universal function approximator,
问题就变成了：这会对计算栈产生什么影响
the question then is what does that, what does that do to the computing stack?
软件会怎么变？会影响哪些行业
What does that happen to software? What are the industries that this could impact,
诸如此类
so on and so forth.
我们几乎立刻就开始做计算机视觉
Almost right away we started working on computer vision.
几乎立刻就开始做机器人
Almost right away we started working on robotics,
还有自动驾驶汽车，因为凭借那种基础能力
self driving cars because that fundamental capability,
你能想象到它可以解决计算机视觉和机器人领域的一些重要问题
you could imagine solving some important problems in the area of computer vision and robotics.
所以我觉得，真正的重大突破其实就是
And so, so I think, I think the the big breakthrough was simply
这件事比 AlexNet 要根本得多
that this is much more foundational than AlexNet.
这是一种全新的做软件的方式，它对处理器
This is a way of doing software and the implications to the processor,
中间件、算法和应用都有深远影响
the middleware, the algorithms, the applications.
就是我现在说的“五层蛋糕”，整个产业技术栈
You know, what I now describe as the five layer cake, that entire industrial stack,
我大概在 15 年前就设想过要把它们全部重塑一遍
I imagine reinventing all altogether about 15 years ago.
这其实就是不断提问
And this is simply about asking questions,
用 first principles 去推理，去问这样的问题
reasoning about things to first principles, asking, you know, questions like,
如果这样，那会怎样？如果这个能变得更好，那又意味着什么
if this, then what if, if this can get better, then so what?
就是对你观察到的东西问出所有最基本的问题
You know, asking all of the basic questions about, about something that you observe,
这真的很有影响力
that's really impactful.
我特别注意到的一点是，你会一路深入
I mean, one of the things that really jumps out at me is to what degree you go all
到非常细枝末节的地方
the way into the weeds.
你读论文，直接和那些提出这些想法的首席科学家
You read the papers, you talk directly to the principal scientists who are sort of
交流
coming up with these things.
你对在座的观众有什么建议吗
Do you have any advice for people in the audience?
我是说，这才是真正的 founder mode，但与此同时你可能
I mean, that's like true founder mode and then at the same time you probably,
你有一个组织，有高管，有人会说
you have an organization and you have executives and you have people who say like,
这是我们的曲线图，我们想沿着这条曲线走
here's the graph we want to stay on this graph.
你知道，有时候这会得罪人。比如
You know, sometimes it ruffles feathers. Like,
关于组织，以及你如何处理这些，你有什么建议吗
do you have any advice for people about an organization and how you navigate that?
说真的，你要怎么建立一个让人能用 first principles 去思考的组织
Really? Like, how do you build an org that allows you to think in first principles?
因为如果 Fortune 500 都这么做
Because if the Fortune 500 did that,
那 Fortune 500 大概会更像 NVIDIA
like the Fortune 500 will probably look a lot more like NVIDIA than not.
但它们并不像你。你打造了一家非常独特的公司
And it doesn't like you. You have built a very unique company.
我的心态，我的心态总是从好奇心开始
My state of mind when I'm my state of mind is always starts with curiosity.
我自己有一大堆问题，当然，跟其他人一样
I have a whole bunch of questions myself and, and of course, like anybody else,
我会去找通往答案的最短路径
I'll seek the shortest path to the answer.
但很多时候，我身边人给出的答案
But oftentimes the, the answers from the people
可能并不能让我满意
that are near me might not be satisfying.
而且我可能还有别的问题，也许他们
And, and I might have other questions and, and maybe they're,
正忙着做别的事，在追求别的目标
they're busy doing something and they're pursuing something.
所以我的第一反应，就是自己去找出满足好奇心的答案
And so my first, my first inclination is to go discover the answers to my own curiosity.
第二点是，如果我发现某些信息，或者某个信息领域
My second is if I find that the information is and that the domain of information or,
某个特定领域，可能对某些人非常重要
you know, particular field could be really important to somebody
也可能对我们公司很重要
and could be important to our company.
那我接下来的想法就是，怎么尽可能多地学习
Then my next inclination is how can I learn as much as possible so
让我能为公司出力，并把它分享给其他所有人
that I could be of service to the company and share with everybody else, you know,
这和你分享知识没什么两样
this is no different than you when you're sharing knowledge.
我是说，我看你的播客，看你的视频，我很喜欢
I mean, I watch your podcast and I watch your videos and I really enjoy them.
你在很多方面都在跟大家分享想法
You're sharing ideas with everybody else in a lot of ways,
我认为 CEO 是在为公司服务
I think a CEO is in service of the company,
为在这里工作的所有人服务
in service of all the people that are working there,
你想用一些洞见去赋能他们
and you want to empower them with some insight.
所以这才是它真正的来源。它与其说是一种管理技巧
And so that's really where it's coming from. It's not so much a management technique,
不如说是一种个性使然
but a personality technique.
你知道，我想赋能你
You know, I want to empower you.
而这是我刚刚观察到的一件非常重要的事
And this is something really important that I just observed.
让我告诉你为什么它这么重要
Let me tell you why it's so important.
之所以要贴近一线、深入细节
Now, part of, part of having to, to be near the ground and be in the weeds,
可以这么说，是因为技术往往很复杂，或者变化非常快
if you will, is because oftentimes the technology is complicated or it's changing really fast.
尤其是变化很快的时候，就像我们所处的世界
And especially when it's changing fast, like, like our world, um,
除非你能真切地感受到实际正在发生什么
unless you have a tactile sensation of what is actually happening,
否则你会觉得一切变化太快，根本理解不了
it could either to you feel like it's just moving way too fast to understand.
但如果你逐渐理解了它的 first principles
But if you understand the first principles of it over time,
那一切就都说得通了，就有点像冲浪
then everything kind of makes sense, you know, it's kind of like surfing,
我猜是这样
I would imagine.
我不会冲浪，但我能想象它有点像冲浪
I don't know how to surf, but I can imagine it's kind of like surfing.
你踏上浪头，在我看来那就是一片混乱
You get on the wave. To me it looks like chaos.
但对冲浪者来说，他们总能掌握好
But to a surfer, you know, somehow they get right.
他们能读懂海浪，知道怎么稳稳站在浪上
They can read the waves and, and they know how to stay on top of it.
所以我觉得当 CEO 跟这非常像
And so I think being CEO is very similar to that.
你得学会冲浪，而要学会冲浪
You know, you have to learn how to surf. In order to learn how to surf,
你就得理解海浪
you have to understand the waves.
你得能读懂风向，还得有好的时机感
You have to be able to read the wind, and you have to have good timing.
而这些都得靠亲自尝试、亲自去做才能获得
And you can't have any of that unless you try, unless you actually do it.
所以一部分是为了让自己了解情况，一部分是为了搞清楚
And so, so partly is, is, um, to inform myself, partly is to, uh, try to figure out,
试着把问题拆解开
you know, what is, try to break down the problem so
好让公司能以可以采取行动的方式去理解它
that the company can learn it in a way that they can do something about.
还有一部分是为了激励其他人
Part of it is by inspiring other people.
这些其实都是在座各位都具备的基本特质
And, you know, it's all those basic traits of all the people in this room.
当上 CEO 后，你不必改变自己的性格或行为方式
You don't have to change your personality or your behavior when you become CEO.
你完全可以继续做自己
It is possible for you to continue to be yourself.
我很久以前学到的一件事
And one of the things that I, that I, I Learned a long time ago, um, and, and I,
我完全不记得是在哪看到的，但作为 CEO 或创始人
I have no idea where I saw this, uh, but, but, um, you know, the CEO or the founders,
你就是你自己
you are the, you.
你在造一辆自己要去开的赛车
You're building a car that you are gonna race.
你要造一辆 F1 赛车
You're gonna build an F1 racer,
但你要按自己能驾驭的方式来造
but you're gonna build it in a way that you can drive.
你应该让车去适应你
You should adapt the car to you.
我记得有人问我，Jensen，如果你
You know, somebody I think asked me, you know, Jensen, if you,
如果你不用传统的管理方法
if you don't use conventional management techniques
和组织方式，你知道会发生什么吗
and organizational techniques you know what's gonna happen
等你离开公司的时候
when you leave the company?
我说，等哪天我在岗位上去世了
Well, you know, when I die on the job someday, you know,
我告诉他们，到时候他们只要为下一任 CEO 重新塑造公司就行
I told them they'll just have to reshape the company for the next CEO.
这之所以是智慧，是因为我们是 F1 车手
And the reason that's wisdom is because we're the F1 drivers, you know,
我们是赛车手，这个世界竞争非常激烈，我们必须坚持
we're the racers and the world is really competitive and we've got to stay.
我们必须赢，必须完成我们的使命
We've got to, you know, we've got to win and we gotta achieve our mission.
所以无论要怎么让车去适应你
And so whatever it takes to fit the car to you,
无论要怎么让组织去适应你，你都得那么做
whatever it takes to fit the organization to you, that's what you gotta do.
至于下一任 CEO，不管他是什么性格，他自己能想明白
And the next CEO, whatever the personality is, they can figure it out.
太精彩了
Amazing.
我是说，任何不适合你的改动，不都会拖慢你
I mean, doesn't it does seem like any change you make to the car will just slow you
让你输掉比赛吗
down and lose you races that, you know, isn't fit to you.
是的，或者说我们一直在根据自己的需要微调这辆车
Yeah. Or we're constantly tweaking the car to our needs.
而这其实就是我一直在做的事
And that's really what I'm doing all the time.
我一直在微调这家公司
I'm constantly tweaking the company,
不断重塑业务流程和运作方式，好让我能
constantly reshaping business processes and the way things work so that I can,
为公司发挥更大的作用
you know, be more effective for the company.
没错。Founder mode。对，founder mode。founder mode 能持续 34 年
True. Founder mode. Yeah, founder mode. Founder mode. Could scale for 34 years.
没错，从 0 做到 5 万亿
That's right. From 0 to 5 trillion.
没有反例。没有
No evidence. No.
我想换个话题，聊聊
I'd love to switch gears to like what, you know, what are the,
你现在最感兴趣的 frontier algorithms 是哪些
what are the frontier algorithms that you're most interested in now?
我很欣赏你既深入到材料科学
I mean, I love that you're all the way down into the material science,
又能一路做到应用层
all the way up into the app level.
你是第一个在台上谈 Open Claw、现在又谈 Hermes Agent 的人
You know, you're the first to speak on stage about Open Claw and now Hermes Agent.
我想请你带我们看看，你的一天大概是怎么过的
I wonder if you can sort of like walk us through a day in the life of like how you
想想不同的阶段，我是说
think about the different stages, I mean,
从材料到芯片，到数据中心，甚至到应用层
going from materials to chips to data centers to even like the app level,
比如人们将如何工作
like how people are going to work.
就像有一种 full-stack AI 工厂的概念
Like there's sort of this idea of a full stack AI factory.
这正是其中一件
Well, this is one of the things that
未来可能最有用的技能
that is probably going to be the most useful skill in the future.
事实上，光是听你谈技术，谈你
And in fact, just in listening to you talk about, about technology and, and you,
如何运用它，你知道，最重要的一点就是系统
your use of it, you know, one of the most important things is systems,
理解系统意识、系统设计、系统组织，嗯
understanding systems awareness, system design, system organization, um,
也就是系统思维
but system thinking.
原因在于，大多数底层的东西
And the reason for that is because most of the low level things that
反正都会由 agents 来完成
that has to be done are going to be done agentically anyways.
它们无论如何都会被自动化
They're going to be automated anyhow.
所以无论是，你知道，在我这一代
And so whether it's, you know, in my generation,
那时是编译芯片、综合晶体管和逻辑门
it's about compiling chips and synthesizing transistors and gates
还有功能模块，而这些现在都能自动综合了
and functional blocks and, and all of that is now synthesized.
所以我们大多数设计师都是系统设计师
And so most of our designers are systems designers.
而在软件方面，大多数软件反正都会由 agents 来完成
In the case of software, most software is going to be done agentically anyhow.
所以你必须更善于对系统进行抽象思考
So you have to be much more able to think abstractly about systems.
你要解决的是什么问题
What are the, what are the, the problems you're trying to solve?
有哪些约束
What are the constraints?
你知道，输入在哪，输出在哪
Where, you know, where's, where's the input, where's the output, you know,
信息从哪里来，嗯
where information coming from, um, what is the rate of,
信息流入和流出系统的速率是多少
of information flowing in and out of the system?
呃，有哪些约束
Uh, what are the constraints?
嗯，你知道，涉及处理器、内存、网络，呃
Um, you know, and so is a processor, is a memory, is a networking, uh, you know,
所以理解这些，呃
and so understanding these, uh,
在足够的技术层面理解这些系统问题，会非常有助于
systems problems at a sufficiently technical level is going to be very helpful to
在座的所有人。我不认为那种方式会
all of the people in this room. And I don't think that that, that way of.
那些基础知识永远都不会变得没用
That fundamental knowledge is ever going to be useless.
我认为它只会越来越有用
I think it's going to be more and more useful.
所以我尽我所能去理解系统
And so I, I try to understand systems the best I can.
有一件事，说到 agents
One of the things, one of the things, speaking of agents,
事实上，我们某种程度上已经有了粗粒度的递归式自我
the fact of the matter is we, we kind of have course level a recursive self
改进，而且每次你使用它
improvement already and the fact that every time you use it,
它都会改进那些 markdown 文件
it improves the markdown files.
每次你使用它，它都会更新它的长期记忆
Every time you use it, it updates its long term memory.
而长期记忆会被处理，要么被压缩，要么被转化为
And the long term memory is being processed either compacted or turned into
知识图谱，等等诸如此类
knowledge graphs or, you know, so on and so forth.
它一直在被改进，呃，你知道，是异步进行的
It's been improved all the time, uh, you know, asynchronously.
所以这个 agent 每次都变得越来越聪明
And so the agent's getting smarter and smarter every time.
但问题依然存在，这也是其中一个
Still the problem is, and this is one of the,
我认为对大家都有帮助去解决的问题是，我们怎样才能
one of the problems that I think would be helpful for everybody to solve is how can
拥有非常非常具体、细粒度的控制，你知道，不靠 RAG
we have very, very specific fine grain control, you know, if not for rags,
不靠条件输入
if not for conditional inputs.
不靠我们所有的提示词
If not for our all of our prompts.
嗯，直接影响到输出，太粗糙了
Um, directly into output was. Was too coarse?
所以我们能够进行条件控制
And so the fact that we can condition,
我们能够把对 agents 的控制一直细化到最终
the fact that we can control the agents all the way down to eventually
当它给出一个方案时，我在方案文件里改一个词
when it comes up with a plan, I change one word in a plan file.
而那一个词只带来增量的变化，不是彻底的改变
And that one word makes a delta difference, not complete difference,
而是具体的改变
but specific difference.
也许是一个像素，也许是一个三角形
Maybe it's one pixel, maybe it's one triangle,
也许是 CAD 文件里的一个元件，也许是一层、一个过孔、一条连线
maybe it's one component in a CAD file, maybe one layer, one via one connection.
然后它会重新生成其余的一切
And then it regenerates everything else.
我认为，那种程度的控制
I think that, that level of control and
以及与 agents 那种程度的协作，将会带来颠覆性的改变
that level of collaboration with agents will be game changing.
我们不需要 agents 做到 100% 准确
We don't need the agents to be 100% accurate,
不需要 100% 高质量，我们才能用它
100% high quality in order for us to use it.
它，你知道，其实就算只有 80%
It could, you know, literally be 80%
然后我们帮它走完剩下的路，也可能它已经完成了 99%
and then we help it the rest of the way or it could be 99%,
我们帮它走完剩下的部分
we help it the rest of the way.
所以我认为可控性可能是我们最需要的
And so I, I think controllability is probably the single biggest breakthrough
各个层面 agents 最大的单点突破
that we need for agents at every single level.
你觉得人们会像，我是说，有了 Hermes 或 Open Claw
Do you think people will like, I mean, with Hermes or Open Claw,
感觉这其实可能事关生死
it feels like that might actually be somewhat existential,
就是说人们应该掌控自己的个人 AGI
like people should control their own personal AGI,
而不该把它外包出去
like they shouldn't outsource that at and.
让它只待在云端，成为别人的 agent
You know, have it be just in the cloud and someone else's agent that, like,
反过来告诉你该做什么，你会更想让它属于自己
kind of tells you what to do, like, you kind of want it to be your own.
是的。这是不是 NVIDIA 如此投入背后的推动力之一
Yeah. Is that part of the thrust behind NVIDIA being so involved?
我想，嗯，首先
And I think, well, first of all, I,
我得理解 agents，因为 agents 就是新的软件
I need to understand agents because agents is the new software.
而这种新软件如何被处理
And how is this new software processed matters a,
对计算机架构非常关键，我们越是深入了解
a lot to computer architecture and the, the more intimate we are about, um,
agents 的本质，以及它和 chatbots 有何不同
the nature of agents and how it's different than, than, uh, chatbots,
也就是它有多大差别
which is how different than, than.
嗯，也许最初只是 inference
Um, maybe inference in the very beginning.
无论我们怎么看待这些处理层
However we think about these processing layers,
我们越深入理解处理的本质
the more intimate we are about the nature of the processing,
就越能设计出更好的系统
the better we could design systems.
我们某种程度上得活在五到十年后的未来
We, we kind of have to live in the future five to 10 years
因为光是造一套系统就要三年左右
because it takes three or so years just to build a system,
再花几年时间把产能拉起来
takes a couple of years to ramp it up and you're dealing
而你希望他们能用上这台计算机
and you would like them to be able to use the computer.
之后再用十年
For 10 years after.
所以你得先在未来里活上一阵子
So you kind of have to live in the future for a while.
所以从 first principles 看，agentic 系统对我们来说就是：工作负载是什么
And so agentic systems for us at the first principles is just what is the workload,
算法是什么
what's the algorithm?
它会怎么演进，瓶颈在哪里
How is it going to evolve, where the bottlenecks, you know,
Amdahl's Law 的问题出在哪，它又如何扩展
where the Amdahl's Law's problems and how does it scale?
并发会怎样？你如何处理 sandbox
What happens to concurrency? How do you deal with sandboxes?
你如何处理 MCP？如何处理工作记忆
How do you deal with MCP? How do you deal with, you know, working memory,
长期记忆
long term memory?
你如何让所有这些自主系统
How do you have all these autonomous systems,
异步系统一直运转
asynchronous systems working all the time?
那么什么样的架构设计才最合理
And so what kind of design architecture makes perfect sense for that?
所以我们必须去把这些搞清楚
And so we have to go and go discover that.
嗯，当然，第二件事是我想让我们自己也用 agents，让
Um, and then of course, the second thing is I want to use agents ourselves to make a
NVIDIA 跑得更快，Boris 就在后面，所以我们
video go faster and so we have, you know, Boris is in the back and, and so we, you.
我们让 cloud code 在 NVIDIA 各处的 sandbox 里自主运行
We've got cloud code autonomously running in sandboxes all over a video.
这真的很棒
And that's really fantastic.
有人用 codec，有人用 code，有人用 cursor
And, and some people use codec, some people use code, some people use cursor,
有人用 cognition
some people use cognition.
我们让百花齐放
And, and we, we let kind of a thousand flowers bloom.
让大家自己选想用的工具，然后我们从
Let people select the tools that they want to use, and then we learn from,
这一切中学习
from all of that.
所以第二部分就是帮公司跑得更快，用好这些工具
And so the second part is just helping the company move faster, use the tools.
他们用得越多，我们就越能学到未来如何把它做得更好
And the more they use it, then we're going to learn about how to make it work better in the future.
而最后一部分，是探索未来的解决方案
And, and the last part is, is discovering the, the future of, of solutions,
面向未来的技术
technology for the future.
也许，当我们看到最早版本的
And maybe, you know, when we, when we saw, when we saw the early versions of,
chain of thought 从 Stanford 出来时，那大概已经是十年前
of chain of thought come out of Stanford is probably a decade ago at this point,
也许八年前
maybe eight years ago.
问题在于
You know, the question is, is how,
它在推理上会有多有效，又有多可扩展
how effective is that going to be in reasoning and how scalable is going to be
以及它对计算机视觉这类领域意味着什么
and what is the implication for example in computer vision
如果我们能从先验知识出发进行推理
if we can reason from prior knowledge and.
然后当然，最大的突破
And then the big breakthrough, of course,
就在于当你把那个小小的领域彻底想透后，你会意识到
just in thinking through that small little domain you come to realize
也许训练一辆自动驾驶汽车并不需要那么多数据
that maybe we don't need as much data for cars to train a self driving car,
这促使我们创造了 Alphamayo
which led us to creating Alphamayo.
它是世界上第一辆会思考的自动驾驶汽车
Which is the world's first thinking self driving car.
只用了大约一百万英里，两百万英里左右
And with just a million miles or so, a couple million miles,
它就是一辆非常出色的自动驾驶汽车
it's an incredibly great self driving car.
原因在于它有点像我们，对吧
And the reason for that is it's kind of like us, right?
我们不需要开那么多英里
We don't need that many miles before.
一生中大部分时候都能开得相当好
We could drive fairly well most of our lives.
原因在于我们有来自语言模型的先验知识
And the reason for that is because we have prior knowledge from our language model
我们能把从未见过的情况分解开
and we can decompose a situation we've never seen before
用我们理解且非常熟悉的东西重新构建它
and build it up out of things that we understood and know very well.
所以这就是一个例子：先看到某件事，然后在一段时间后
And so, so that's an example of seeing something and then realizing the impact some,
才意识到它的影响
some time later.
当 agentic 系统出现时，非常
When the agentic systems came along, it's very,
非常清楚，大语言模型显然需要记忆
very clear that obviously a large language models needs memory,
需要先验知识，需要工具，需要与其他 agents 联网的方式
it needs prior knowledge, it needs tools, it needs ways to network with other agents.
所以你知道，一旦你看到一些早期迹象
And so that kind of, you know, that once you see some early indicators
并且能够推演未来，就能帮你跃入
and you're able to reason about the future helps you get a leap, you know, into,
未来
into the future.
我感觉自己开始在 NVIDIA 身上看到一种模式
I feel like there's this pattern that I'm starting to see around, around NVIDIA.
就好像你看到一个问题，出现了一种新算法
It's like you see a problem, there's a new algorithm,
有一些新的事情正在发生
there's some new thing happening.
然后你其实就在开源那一线
And then actually you're right there with open source.
我记得 Open Claw 出来的时候，大家说它不安全
I mean, I remember when Open Claw came out and people said it was unsafe,
但你们推出了一套沙箱式的工具包
but you guys came out with sandboxing sort of toolkit
它能包裹任何 harness 让它变得安全
that like surrounds any harness and makes it safe.
当我看到 Open Claw 时，我的第一反应是，首先，我去了解了它
When I saw Open Claw, my first thought was, well, first of all, I learned about it.
然后呢？然后
And then? And then.
你知道，不需要太多想象力
You know, without, without much imagination,
你就意识到我们刚刚设计出了现代计算机
you just realized we just designed the modern computer.
这就是那个将承载大语言模型的操作系统
This this is the operating system that's going to hold a large language model and
在很多方面，Open Claw 对我来说是一个非常 Linux 式的时刻
and in a lot of ways Open Cloud to me was very Linux moment to me.
现在每个人都能构建自己的 AI，我为此非常兴奋
And now everybody can build their own AI. And I was so excited about that.
我们联系了 Peter，说，嘿，你知道
And we contacted Peter and we said, hey, you know,
NVIDIA 所有的工程师都是你的工程师
all of NVIDIA's engineers are your engineers.
这就是我对 Peter 说的话。你家门口停着一艘战舰
That's what I told Peter. You got this battleship outside your house.
你可以按你想要的方式拆解问题，我们会按你希望的方式贡献
You, you, you know, break down the problem as you desire and we'll contribute as, as you wish.
对 Hermes 团队也是一样，你知道
Same thing with the, the, the Hermes team, you know,
我对他们正在做的工作非常兴奋
and I'm so excited about the work that they're doing.
我确实认为，世界需要让每个人都有能力构建自己的 AI
I, I do think that the world needs the ability for everybody to build their own AI.
当然，你完全可以做到
And you could, you could, of course.
我鼓励每个人尽可能多地使用云服务
And I encourage everybody to, to use cloud services as much as possible.
每个人都应该用 ChatGPT 和 Claude，对，每个人都应该用
Everybody should use ChatGPT and Claude and right everybody should use that and
但如果你需要构建自己的 AI，因为你是一家公司
but if you if you need to build your own AI because you're a company and
需要构建自己领域专用的 AI
and you need to build your own domain specific AIS.
现在你有了 Hermes，也有了 Open Claw
Now you have Hermez and you have Open Claw.
你有各种各样的选择，有 LangChain、Deep Agent
You've got all kinds of, you got Lang Chain, Deep Agent,
你有所有这些不同的方式，对吧
you got all these different ways, right,
来构建自己的 AI，坦率说这相对容易
to build your own AI and it's it's quite frankly relatively easy
因为软件本身很聪明，你知道
because the software is smart, you know.
AI 很聪明，正因为 AI 如此聪明，你可以轻松地对它进行适配
And so AI is smart, and therefore AI must be so smart, you could adapt it easily.
所以我认为，我们想要
And so I, I think that that we want,
我们想鼓励每个人、每家公司去构建自己的 AI
we want to encourage everybody and every company to build their own AIS.
而且，谁知道开源这一点会带来怎样的创新
And, and, um, and who knows what innovation will come from the fact that it's open source.
我觉得所有的优势都在于构建自己的 AI
I feel like all the alpha is in building your own AI.
我是说，如果别人用的是现成的东西
I mean, if someone else is using whatever is off the shelf,
而你有一个能递归地自我改进的东西，你知道
but you're you have a thing that can recursively self improve and it is you know,
我是说，有些人对 Markdown 文件很不以为然
I mean the mechanic people are very flippant about market markdown files.
他们会说，哦，哈哈，那只是文本。但是
They say like, oh, haha, it's just text. But, like,
文本就是智能，我们已经身处一个不同的世界
text is intelligence and we're in a different.
语言就是思想。对，对，语言就是思想
Words are thoughts. Yeah, yeah, words are thoughts. Yeah.
事实上，你可以试着不用语言去思考
And it turns out you can try to try to think without words.
对，那更难
Yeah, that's harder.
再换个话题，其实很多人，只要你动了他们的奶酪
So switching gears again, I mean, a lot of people are anytime you move the cheese,
大家就会有点担心
people get a little worried.
智能将会随取随用，这真的很棒
Intelligence is gonna be on tap, which is really awesome.
我觉得这对在座的每个人都是好事
I think it bodes well for everyone in this room.
你觉得经济会发生什么变化？你觉得
Um, what do you think changes about the economy? What do you think, you know,
从更宏观的角度会发生什么
happens in sort of a broader sense?
显然，我要说的是，这种影响并不均衡
Uh, obviously what I'm gonna say is uneven.
有些，我们会自动化一些任务
Uh, there are some, uh, you know, we're gonna automate tasks,
我们会自动化认知类的任务
we're gonna automate cognitive tasks.
如果这个任务是，有人打来电话，说了一堆话
If that task is, uh, somebody makes a phone call and and sends a bunch of words.
通过电话传到你这里，而你的工作就是给出回应
You know, across the phone to you and your job is to provide a response.
而如果所有信息都触手可及，因为你
And, and if all the information is at your fingertips because you,
手上有整个数据库，你应该能够
you have all the database here and you should be able to,
完整地回答那个问题，那这个任务就会被自动化掉
to answer that question completely in that case that task will be automated away.
好，先把这个放一放
Okay, ignoring that for a second.
不是说你，不是说我们忽略了这一点
Not that not that you, not that we, we ignored this.
但我的意思是，我要回答的问题是
But my, my point is, I'm going to answer the question about,
真正巨大的机会，会有很多任务被自动化掉
about really the great opportunity and so many tasks will be automated away,
很多工作，每一份工作都会
many jobs, every single job will be,
发生改变，同时会出现一大批新的工作
will change and there'll be a whole bunch of new jobs.
这一点我觉得我们是知道的
And that, that I think we know.
归根结底是这样，证据会证明，而且这完全说得通
The bottom line is this, the evidence would show that and it makes perfect sense
AI 和自动化正在到处创造就业
that AI and automation is creating jobs everywhere.
关于 AI 消灭工作的说法，恰恰说反了
The narrative about AI destroying jobs is exactly backwards.
AI 消除的是任务
AI eliminate tasks.
AI 把任务自动化掉，但不一定会消灭工作岗位
AI automates tasks away but it doesn't necessary doesn't necessarily eliminate jobs.
原因在于
And the reason for that is because the,
一个人的工作是有目的的，而这个目的包含许多任务
the job of a person has a purpose and that purpose has many tasks.
其中一些任务可以被自动化，但很多任务不行
Some of those tasks could be automated away. Many of those tasks cannot be.
所以证据表明，看看现在，我们已经把编程自动化了
And so the evidence suggests that here we are, we've automated coding,
这是一项任务，但软件工程师这个岗位似乎还在增长，对吧
which is a task, but the job of a software engineer appears to be growing, right?
软件工程师岗位的数量同比增长了 10%
The number of software engineer jobs year over year has increased 10%.
读取放射影像这项任务已经被自动化了
The task of reading radiology scans has been automated,
但放射科的岗位在过去几年里增长了大约 20%
but the number of radiology jobs has increased some 20 percent in the last several
尽管 AI 已经接管了整个领域
years, even though AI has taken over the whole field.
原因在于，积压的病人数量非常庞大
And the reason for that is because the backlog of patients is incredibly high.
现在，医生和医院可以接收更多的病人，而为了接收更多
Now, doctors and hospitals could admit a lot more patients in order to admit a lot
病人，你就需要更多护士、更多放射科医生
more patients, you need more nurses, more radiologists.
软件也是一样，积压的点子
And so the same thing with software, with the backlog of ideas,
积压的雄心和抱负如此之多，以至于
the backlog of ambition and aspiration is so high that
如果我们能把编程这项任务自动化掉
if we can automate away ta the task of programming,
我们就能雇更多软件工程师去做更多事情
we could hire more software engineers to do more things.
我们可以更有野心
We could be more ambitious.
各行各业都是一样的道理
Same thing just across the board.
有人说 Harvey 会消灭所有律师助理的岗位
They said Harvey is going to eliminate all of the paralegal jobs
律师的数量会减少
and the number of lawyers will be reduced.
结果律师助理的数量疯狂增长
Turns out paralegals are growing like crazy.
原因在于，积压的诉讼案件非常多
And the reason for that is because the backlog of lawsuits is really high
现在这些律所要处理更多的案子
and now these law firms to get a lot more cases through.
为了做到这一点，你得雇更多的人
In order to do so, you gotta hire more people.
所以这是一个生产力推动增长的经典例子
And so this is a classic example of productivity increasing growth.
增长的提升带来更多就业
Increasing growth drives more employment.
这就是为什么今天的就业比我
This is the reason why there's more employment today than there was
刚毕业那会儿还要多
when I first came out of school.
我们聊了很多关于软件和 agents 的话题
So we've been talking a lot about software and agents.
NVIDIA 另一个非常前沿、令人兴奋的方向
Another really exciting thing that NVIDIA is all the way out on the edge on is
其实是实体机器人
actually physical robots.
你觉得还有多远？我记得你过去甚至说过就在今年
You know how far out? I think in the past you might have even said this as soon as this year.
关于什么时候能有实用的机器人，你最新的想法是什么？是的
What's the latest thinking on, you know, when can we expect practical robotics? Yeah,
我看到我们能生成视频的那一刻
the moment that I saw us generating video.
那对我来说是个重要时刻。当我开始看到
That was a great moment for me. The moment that I and I start,
我看到我们能生成视频
I saw us generating video.
我是说，我们最早做了 autoregressive GANs 的开创性工作，对吧
I mean, we did the original work on auto progressive Gans, okay?
我们也很早就做了 conditional GANs 的开创性工作
And we did the original work on conditional Gans long
早在外界第一批视频被生成之前
before the first videos were generated outside
比人们看到的早了几年，在我们实验室里我们已经在跑了
that people saw a couple of years earlier inside our labs we were driving.
一个完全由视频和计算机生成的模拟器
A simulator completely generated by video and computer,
完全由神经网络生成
completely generated by neural networks.
所以当我看到我们能生成关节运动的那一刻
And so the moment I saw us generating articulation,
如果我能生成手指移动的视频
if I can generate video of a finger moving,
如果我能生成一只手拿起玻璃杯的视频
if I could generate video of a hand picking up a glass,
为什么我不能让机器人做同样的事
why can't I cause a robot to do the same?
所以当我看到生成式 AI 成为现实的那一刻
And so the moment I saw that generative AI happening,
我意识到机器人关节运动就在眼前了
I realized that robotics articulation was around the corner.
所以现在的问题是，机器人要怎么理解，呃
And so now the question is, you know, how is the robot going to understand, uh, uh,
生成符合物理定律的动作
to generate motions that obey the laws of physics?
它怎么理解因果关系
How's it, how does it understand causality?
呃，它怎么理解摩擦力、张力
Um, how does it understand, you know, friction, tension?
它怎么理解物理定律
How does it understand the laws of physics?
于是这让我们踏上了创造现在所谓 physical AI 的旅程
And so it started us down the journey of creating what we call physical AI now,
现在大家都叫它 physical AI，为了 physical AI
and everybody calls it physical AI and physical AI,
我们开始研发 World Foundation Model
we started working on World Foundation Model,
一个理解物理定律和世界如何运作的 AI
an AI that understands the laws of physics and how the world works.
我们也踏上了做机器人的旅程
And we started down the journey of working on robotics.
我会说机器人的 ChatGPT 时刻其实几年前就已经发生了
I would say the ChatGPT moment of robots happened a couple year years ago already.
哇
Wow.
原因是，还记得 ChatGPT 刚出来的时候
And, and the reason for that is remember when Chat GPT first came out,
它没做什么有生产力的事，也没做什么有用的事
it didn't do anything productive, it didn't do anything useful.
但它打开了我们对可能性的想象
But it opened our imagination about what's possible.
我会说几年前，机器人四处走动
And I would say a couple of years ago, you know, robots walking around,
我们能做强化学习
that we could do reinforcement learning,
为它做微调、扎根于物理，这些其实几年前就已经发生了
fine tune it for and grounded in physics really happened a couple of years ago.
那现在呢？我们需要做什么
So now what? What do we need to do?
我们需要做和现在为 agentic 系统所做的一模一样的事
We need to do all the same things that we're doing now for agentic systems.
我们必须创造环境让它们在其中学习、评估
We have to create environments for them to learn in to eval in eval against.
所以我们必须做 real to sim 来创造环境
And so we have to do real to SIM to create environments, we have to do.
我们必须生成基于仿真的模拟器
We have to generate simulators that are based on simulation,
扎根于物理的仿真，以及生成式的物理仿真
grounded physics simulation, as well as generative physics simulations.
所以 Isaac Sim、Cosmos 以及我们在
And so Isaac Sim Cosmos and all the work that we do in
这个领域做的所有工作都和仿真有关
that area is related to simulation.
然后最后一部分是 sim to real
And then the last part is SIM to real.
这部分和强化学习有关
And so that part has something to do with reinforcement learning,
让它扎根于物理，扎根于机器人所需的所有机电系统
grounding it on physics, grounding it on all the electro mechanical systems that
机器人所需要的这些系统
that robots require.
所以这三个基本系统，我认为构建起了评估，可以说是
And so, but these three basic system, I think builds up the eval, if you will, the,
机器人的后训练
the, the, the post training of, of robotics.
我认为我们很快就会看到它
And I think we're, we're going to see it right around the corner.
太棒了。physical AI 最先会在哪里
Amazing. Where does physical AI show up first in a way
以真正有经济意义的方式出现
that's really economically real?
你已经看到了吗
Are you seeing that already?
我们推测机器人会到来，并判断
We conjecture that, uh, that robotics was gonna come along and decided
机器人第一个既有足够大市场、呃
that the first application of robotics that has both a large enough market, um,
又有相对标准化技术、能让我们规模化并转动飞轮的应用
relatively standardized technology so that we could scale and get the flywheel going.
呃，同时又有真正经济价值的，就是自动驾驶汽车
Um, and has real economic value was self driving cars.
所以在 Waymo 里、在 Tesla，我们 NVIDIA 的芯片在车里
And so inside Waymo, our chips from NVIDIA at Tesla, we were in the car,
现在我们在数据中心里
now we're in the data center.
Mercedes，我们在数据中心里，也带着软件栈在车里
Mercedes, we're in the data center. We're in the car with the software stack.
我们做了 Alphamayo，还把它开源了
We worked on Alphamayo and we open sourced it.
我们之所以开源自动驾驶的整套技术栈
And the reason why we open sourced the self driving car stack is
是因为农业需要它，邮件配送需要它
because you need it for agriculture, you need it for mail delivery,
仓储的 AMR 也需要它
you need it for warehouse AMRS.
自主导航有太多不同的应用场景
There's so many different ways that you could apply autonomous navigation
但没有哪个市场大到能撑起一个自动驾驶汽车市场
and none of those markets are big enough to be a self driving car market.
我们觉得它足够多样
And we thought it was sufficiently diverse
值得我们为它打造整套技术栈
that we would create the whole stack for it.
所以我们在各种不同场景里都在做自动驾驶
And so we're working with autonomous vehicles in all kinds of different places.
我们的机器人业务、自动驾驶汽车业务
Our robotics business, autonomous vehicle business,
基本上就是 physical AI 业务，规模差不多快到 100 亿美元了
basically physical AI business is probably almost, it's like $10 billion.
所以它现在已经非常非常大了
So it's really, really big already.
这很可能会成为全世界最大的产业之一
Likely this will be one of the largest industries in the world
它不会只用两三年就成型
and it'll take longer than a couple, 2, 3 years.
但也用不了十年
It'll take less than 10.
所以这会是我们下一个千亿美元级的业务。太惊人了
And so this will, this will be our next hundred billion dollar business. Amazing.
我想花点时间
Um, I wanna take a moment.
我觉得在座的正是最合适的人群
Uh, I think this is the exact right crowd to, uh, you know,
或许我们可以在这里一起欢迎 Jensen 加入 X
maybe as an arena we can welcome Jensen to X.
欢迎来到 X。你发了第一条帖子
Welcome to X. I mean, you made your first post, uh,
也谢谢你的引领
and thank you for your leadership.
你看，这恰好说明我有多内向
You know, that just, that, just, that shows you how introverted I am.
我直到 2026 年才在 X 上发第一条帖子
It took me until 2026 to have the first post on X.
我大概是地球上最后一个这么做的人了
You know, it's I'm probably the last human on earth that that did it.
但我发的那条对我太重要了
But, but what I posted was too important to me and too important to the,
对整个行业、对整个世界都太重要了
to the industry and too important to the world.
所以我克服了自己的害羞，在 X 上发出了第一条内容
And so, so I, I over overcame my, my shyness and, and put my first thing out on X.
不，真的谢谢你的引领
No, thank you for your leadership.
open source、open weights、开源模型，对我们来说都极其重要
I mean, open source, open weights, open source models are incredibly important for,
对我们在座每个人想做的事都很重要，我们都想创办创业公司
I mean, what all of us in this room want to do, like we want to create startups.
是啊，要不是有开源，移动云产业根本不会出现
Yeah, if not for open source, the mobile cloud industry would have never happened.
要不是有开源，要不是有 Linux，要不是有 Kubernetes，要不是有这一切
If not for open, if not for Linux, if not for Kubernetes, if not for all of these,
这些平台，要不是有 TensorFlow，更重要的是 PyTorch，对吧
you know, platform, if not for Tensorflow or more important Pytorch, right?
还有早期版本的 Caffe，对吧
The and the early versions of a cafe, right?
Torch，还有 Theano
Torch, I mean, all of the theano,
记住，这些早期版本全都是开源的
remember the early versions of all those were all open source.
要不是有这一切，我们怎么可能有现代 AI
If not for all of that, how would we have modern AI?
谢谢你的引领，你的声音非常重要。谢谢
Well, thank you for your leadership, and your voice is incredibly important. Thank you.
在结束前，我真的很有共鸣，你的故事打动了我
Before we go, I feel like we, I just really resonate with your story.
我想在座每个人，都很想听听你一路走来的智慧
I think that everyone here, but I mean, would love the wisdom of, you know,
你走到今天这段历程的智慧
your journey coming here.
基于你现在看到的这一切，年轻人现在应该学什么
I mean, what should a young person learn now given all the things that you're seeing,
面对那些即将在社会中扎根的算法
all the algorithms that are gonna take hold in society?
年轻人现在应该学什么
Um, what should a young person learn now
基于你所看到的，什么才会依然重要
that will still matter based on what you're seeing?
我今天看到的一些东西
Well, some of the things that I saw today
还有今天遇到的一些创业者，真的让我非常受鼓舞
and some of the starters I met today was really, really quite, quite encouraging.
而最大的收获当然是
And, and, and the thing that, that the big takeaway is, of course,
那些简单的东西会被自动化掉
the simple stuff is going to get automated away.
我说的简单东西，指的是软件，也就是写代码
And when I say simple stuff, I mean software, you know, coding.
那种想法，就是你会去
The idea that you would, you would do a,
坐在电脑前解决问题，你实际上
you would solve a problem by sitting in front of a computer and you're, you're,
是在一行一行地写代码
you're actually writing, you know, writing code.
这种做法显然会被自动化掉
That concept is obviously going to get automated away.
在我这一代人成长的时候
Um, you know, in my generation when I was, when I was growing up,
我们得做长除法
we had to do long division.
天哪，现在谁还需要学长除法呢
I mean, for god sakes, who has to learn long division, you know?
所以那玩意儿被自动化掉了
And so that got coded away, that got automated away.
所以我觉得简单的东西会被自动化掉
And so I think the simple stuff is going to get automated away,
但那些难题，那些硬科学，物理、化学、生物
but the hard problems, the hard sciences, physics, chemistry, biology, you know,
计算机科学、计算机工程，还有系统思维，你懂的，所有这些
computer science, computer engineer, during systems thinking, you know, all, and, and.
尤其是那些与难题相交叉的领域，永远不会消失
And particularly the domains that are intersecting those hard problems will never go away.
所以 AI 是一个了不起的工具，能让我们更有野心
And so AI is just an incredible tool that helps us become even more ambitious,
更急切地去解决这些极其庞大
even more, um, impatient about solving these extraordinarily large
又极其困难的问题
and incredibly hard problems.
比以往更甚
Than before.
你看我这一代人，我刚毕业的时候
And so, you know, if you, if you look at my generation, when I first graduated,
一个芯片设计师设计的芯片大概只有 1000 个晶体管
a chip designer would design a chip with maybe 1,000 transistors,
而那已经算是很大的芯片了
and that would be a very large chip.
而如今，设计上万亿晶体管的芯片，甚至都不算什么
You know, now, designing a trillion transistor chips is not even, you know,
如果有人告诉我，Jensen，我们下一款芯片是万亿晶体管
if somebody would have told me, Jensen, our next chip is a trillion transistor,
我会说，好啊，这没什么大不了的
I said, okay, you know, it's not a thing.
原因就在于我们如此有野心
And the reason for that is because we are so ambitious.
现在，问题的规模、任务的规模，已经不再是障碍
Now, the, the, the scale of the problem, the scale of the task is no longer a matter.
所以你不用去操心，要写多少代码
And so you don't have to worry about, about, you know, how much coding,
要多少工程师，你不必
how many engineers, you don't have to,
你再也不用去想这些事了
you don't have to think about those things anymore.
你只需要去想，你要解决的问题到底是什么
You just have to think about what is the, what is the problem you have to solve.
所以我认为，那些深科技的东西、深科学的东西，理解
And so I think that the deep, deep tech stuff, the deep science stuff, understanding,
理解技术与社会议题之间的交叉点
understanding the intersection between technology and social issues,
理解市场的空白、缺口和机会
understanding market, market gaps and, and holes, opportunities.
我认为这一切依然存在
I think all of that still exists.
你的系统思维越强
And, and the better you are at systems thinking so
越能调度上百万个 agents 自主地解决问题
that you could orchestrate millions of agents solving problems autonomously,
你就越占优势
the better off you are.
这就是为什么系统思维会如此重要
And so that's why system thinking is going to be so important.
除此之外，我认为这个世界仍会不断给我们
But otherwise, I think the world's going to continue to have a lot of great
留下很多值得解决的重大挑战
challenges for us to solve.
还是按老办法去上学，留在学校里，留在学校里
Go to school the same old way, you know, stay in school. Stay in school.
我通常喜欢在结尾时让你望向台下的人群
I guess I usually like to end with you're looking out on the crowd.
台下有很多人，我一开场的时候就说
There are a lot of people who, I mean, I started this, the opener with like,
老实说，我看着人群，看到的人跟我们本质上并没有什么不同
I honestly look in the crowd and I see people who are not different than us per se.
我们其实就是很技术型，热爱系统
You know, we actually just are technical and like love systems.
谢谢你
You know, thank you.
谢谢
Thank you.
你会给这个房间里的人什么建议
What advice would you give to this room of, you know,
你在这个房间里能看到自己的影子
and you see yourself in this in this room and like,
我很好奇，如果你能发一封电报
I'm curious what you would say if you could send a telegram,
给 18 到 22 岁的自己传一条信息，那会是什么
a message to the 18 to 22 year old version of yourself, what would that be?
我可以确切地告诉你我当时的感受
I could tell you exactly how I felt.
当我第一次，当 NVIDIA 刚成立时
When I first, when NVIDIA first founded and,
我们三个人一起创业，我当时的感受是
and the three of us started the thing I felt at the time is there was
有太多东西我需要懂、需要学，而我都还不会
so much for me to know and so much for me to learn and I didn't know it.
我刚才跟你说过，那个年代没有 YouTube
And I was telling you earlier, there at the time there was, there were no YouTube,
也没有 YC
there's, you know, no YC.
没人教你怎么创办一家公司
Nobody's teaching you how to start a company.
于是我去书店买了一本书
And so I went to the bookstore and I bought a book.
书名就叫《如何创办一家公司》
And the book said how to start a company.
可惜那本书大概有 500 页那么厚，所以我
Unfortunately, the book was like 500 pages long and, and so I, you know,
我心想，等我读完的时候
I figured by the time I read it, you know,
公司都倒闭了，Lori 和我也早破产了
I'd be out of business and LA Laurie and I'd be out of money.
所以读它根本没意义
And so there's no sense reading it.
但我记得非常
But the thing that the thing I remember very,
非常清楚的一件事是，我去融资时有多害怕，因为我觉得
very vividly is that how scared I was to go raise money because I felt
我即将要面对一群人
that I was about to talk to a bunch of people
而我不知道怎么回答他们的问题
and I didn't know how to answer their questions.
这是真的，即便到今天，我也几乎不知道怎么回答他们的问题
And it's true. And I barely know how to answer their questions even today.
但我学到的是，这些事其实都不重要
But the thing that I Learned is none of that stuff matters.
事实证明，你永远都会有自己不懂的东西
As it turns out and, and you're always going to have things that you don't know.
而每一天，世界都在变，技术都在变
And every single day, the world is changing, technology is changing.
显然，这是过去 60 年里最适合创业的时代
Obviously, this is the greatest time in the last 60 years to start a company.
整个行业都变了，是一次彻底的重置
The whole industry has changed. It's a complete reset.
从技术角度看，人类历史上最重要的一项技术
From a technology perspective, the single most important technology in human history,
也就是计算机，已经被彻底重置了
the computer, has been completely reset.
所以这绝对是最适合创业的时刻
And so this is absolutely the single greatest time to start a company.
我真的很羡慕你们所有人
And I'm, I'm, I'm jealous of all of you and, and,
羡慕你们面前的这些机会
and the opportunities you have ahead.
这真的会很精彩。所以一方面，这是绝佳的时机
I mean, it's going to be incredible. So it's the perfect time on the one hand.
另一方面，技术变化得太快，所以问题是
On the other hand, the technology is changing so fast and so the question is,
对你来说，什么才是对的心态
what's the right feeling for you?
我前面讲过我们的故事，讲过我去买那本书的事
And eventually, and I told you the story of us, of me buying the other book,
那本教材。我觉得那种心态和感受
the textbook, I think the psychology and the feeling
就是我今天面对所有新体验、新技术
that I have today on all of the new experiences and the new technology
新市场和新格局时的感受
and new markets and new dynamics.
我看着它，会说，这很重要
I look at it and I say, this is important.
我得去学它，得为它做点什么
I've got to go learn it and I've got to go do something about it.
而且我最好尽快动手
And I better get to it as fast as I can.
这能有多难呢
And how hard can it be?
我一直有这种感觉，这能有多难
I always had this feeling, how hard can it be?
说实话，它比你想的要难得多
And truth be told, it is way harder than you think.
但你不希望自己的脑子停在那儿
And, but you don't want your mind to be, to be there.
你希望自己的心态是：这能有多难
You want your mind to be, how hard can it be
然后让那些苦一点一点地来
and let the suffering come to you a little bit at a time.
别去想它会有多难，然后让这些想法
You know, don't, don't imagine how hard it's gonna be and let all of
全变成焦虑，最后什么都不做
that turn into anxiety and not doing something about it.
你要在脑子里想的是：这能有多难
You want to imagine your head, how hard can it be?
我现在有一大堆——
You know, I got a whole bunch of eight,
反正我有一堆 AI agents 在帮我
I got a bunch of AI agents helping me anyways.
所以这能有多难？然后你就开始动手去做
And so how hard can it be? And then you get going on working on it.
所以这大概就是一个创业者该有的心态
And so that's probably the, the attitude of an entrepreneur.
你会在路上学到很多东西
You, you know, you have to learn a bunch of stuff along the way.
你相信自己的学习能力
You believe in your ability to learn, which is, you know,
而学习就是最强大的超能力
learning is the single greatest superpower.
如果你带着“这能有多难”的心态去做
And if you go into it with the attitude, how hard can it be?
别人能做到，我也能做到
If anybody can do it, I can do it.
你只要清楚它会很难
And just realize that it will be hard
然后靠韧性每天去克服它
and you just have to have the resilience to overcome it every single day.
你不用一天就征服整个人生，你只要熬过那个早上
You don't have to overcome life in one day. You just have to overcome that morning.
那个早上，你只要今天先撑过今天
That morning, you know, you have to overcome today, today.
所以这没什么大不了的
And so it's not a big deal.
先熬过今天，然后一步步朝明天努力
Just get through today, wait till right, work towards tomorrow,
继续追逐你的梦想，其他的一切也一样
keep following your dreams and the rest of everything.
只要你坚持得够久，你懂的，就成了 NVIDIA
If you stick, if you stick with it long enough, I, uh, you know, NVIDIA happens.
所以，如果说我能给出什么智慧的话
And so, you know, I think that the wisdom that I can, if there's anything,
韧性大概就是最重要的那一样东西
is resilience is probably the single most important thing.
如果你相信某件事，就去做，把你的脑子
And if you believe in something, just get going on it and get your mind, uh,
别再因为某些原因把自己拦在追求它的路上
you know, out of, out of keeping your, yourself from pursuing it because of,
不管是恐惧、焦虑、缺乏自信，还是别的什么
you know, fear or anxiety or lack of confidence or whatever it is and
你只要告诉自己：我会一路学着走到那儿。Jensen
that you're just going to tell yourself, I'm going to learn my way there. Jensen,
Huang，各位。好了，大家，谢谢
Wong, everybody. Alright, guys, thank.
非常感谢你们。是的，谢谢大家
You thank you so much. Yes. Thank you, guys.